Yeah.
And hello, everybody.
Good afternoon.
This is Dominic Zurlo with the
Department of Health.
And we are here for the Equity Access and
Cultural Considerations Committee and we
have DezBaa is the chair.
We have just let everybody who is in the
waiting room in.
It usually takes a minute or so for that
to happen.
And so please just give folks a few
moments to join in.
We are doing this as a hybrid meeting.
So we do have a few people here in Santa
Fe and we are at the Gary Carruthers
Building today in the Yucca Room.
If there's anyone on their way who is
listening in,
please come on in and join us.
And other than that,
I will turn this on over to DezBaa.
And we do have DezBaa,
just so that you're aware.
We have a few folks,
non department staff that are on
attending.
We have Jessica Eden,
Kate Hawk and Catherine Sanchez and we
have a few other people looks like
they're trying to join Don Mosher.
And so and with that,
everyone else is either here in the room
if you wanted to do introductions and
I'll pass this on over to you and the
meeting is now yours, Despa.
Thank you, Dominic, and thank you, Johnny,
for passing the mic.
Hello.
Yeah.
Hey, everybody, please, definitely,
if you are not aware of that this meeting
is happening today and you are in Santa Fe,
please come over to the Carruthers
Building.
It's the State Records Library.
It's on your way to the ITT.
If you have a kid at SSFSPC or whatever,
the Santa Fe Public School system.
So it's the same kind of Rd., same area,
same place, Officer Rios.
So definitely come over here.
My name is DezBaa.
Hi everyone, Thank you.
Welcome for attending.
Weather digitally or in person.
We have a lot of work still left to do in the coming year,
but I wanted to open this up to the
communities,
the community space here in person.
And then also making sure that we were
able to include everyone,
as many people as we can at this moment.
I definitely wouldn't mind if everyone
else were to introduce themselves and
just to kind of have Johnny V pointing the camera and passing the mic.
Do you want staff first?
It doesn't matter, however,
just text it to leave sentence.
Is it not working again?
Do you want me to jiggle it?
I think I think it works Whitlet.
Technical difficulty.
This is an emotional difficulty.
My name is Gregory Evans.
I'm an independent researcher and home ecologist with no affiliations.
Santa Fe Resident Air Support Departments committee recommendations along with
emerging research and best practices.
Cyrus Rodman, associate environmental scientist with
the department.
Good afternoon, everyone.
Brenda Martinez,
I'm the Deputy Director at the Center for
Medical Cannabis Psilocybin.
Good afternoon.
Jorge Gonzalez,
Medical Psilocybin program Manager.
Hi there, Leslie Peterson,
Senior compliance Officer.
Good afternoon.
My name is Hanifanaya Washington.
I'm here representing the Psychedelic Mental Health Access Alliance,
of which I'm the Co director.
Good afternoon.
I'm Robert Truckner,
medical director for the program.
I'm Johnny Moushey and I'm management analyst.
Yeah.
Oh, and once again,
I'm Dominic Zurlo and I'm the director
for the Center for Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin.
And then if we have individuals who are
online who would like to introduce
yourselves, if you don't, if you can,
please raise your hand and then we will
unmute you and I'll put the directions in the chat.
Just a moment.
All right, And 1st,
we've got Kate Hawk and your mic should
be enabled.
Hi everyone, I'm Kate Hawk.
I'm here in Santa Fe now,
but what's relevant for this committee is
lived and worked for 40 years with the Navajo Nation and did substance abuse
prevention programs,
ran the Native American Trauma Project
and started a school for Navajo kids.
So especially interested in in that
community.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Thanks, Kate.
And next, we've got Don Moser.
And Don, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Hi, I'm Don Moser, I live in Las Vegas,
NM and very glad to be a part of this
committee and and the program that's
evolving here.
So thank you so much.
So thanks, Don.
And next, we've got Raymond Gallegos.
Hello, everyone.
Raymond Gagas here.
I'm the systems and data analyst for
Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin Bureau.
Thanks, Raymond.
And next, we've got Jessica Eden.
Jessica, you can unmute when ready.
Hello, I'm Jessica Eden,
I'm a licensed psychedelic therapist in
Colorado and also dually licensed in New
Mexico.
And so I am actually just here to learn
and listen.
So thank you for allowing me to be here.
And then we also have in the chat,
we have Catherine or Kathy Sanchez,
who's the Bureau Chief at Workers
Compensation,
Administration and Medical Cost
Containment.
And thank you for joining us today, Kathy.
Thank you all for being here and taking
the time out of your day to be present.
I know some of you might be pulling
double duty, triple duty,
so I really appreciate it.
This is definitely very important work
and part of the reason for us convening
is to gather the multitude and decades
and years of wisdom in working with this
medicine.
And but more importantly,
real life outreach outcomes and
everything that everyone has done to pull
together our resources and their internal
intellect into figuring out how we're
going to make sure that this is available
in different capacities for the state of
New Mexico specifically.
But you know, this has broader reach of,
you know, next states, next steps,
etcetera.
So if you don't mind, Dominic,
to kind of maybe give us a little bit of
a recap where I,
I don't want to like overstate something,
but you can also correct me.
I know that we are for those listening,
working on the tribal liaison,
there's a tribal liaison with the
Department of Health.
So we're essentially respectfully making
sure that we take the right steps to
contact and to communicate and possibly
collaborate with the tribal sovereign
nations in represented in New Mexico.
So if anyone is is waiting for that
moment to happen, don't worry,
we're all waiting with you.
These things do take time.
And so we're we're waiting on that.
And then we also have some updates from
the past few sessions.
And if you don't mind, Dominic,
for giving us that update.
Thank you, Desba.
So one of the things that we're doing
right now and we've been working with our
tribal liaison is just last week on
Wednesday and Thursday,
our Tribal liaison hosted a virtual
session for some of the tribal
governments to be able to hear about
different programs within the Department
of Health.
And so we were able to present about the
program.
And one of the things that we brought up
is that we still have two positions open
on the Advisory Board.
And so we're actively seeking
applications specifically from
populations that have been underserved.
And we want to ensure that one of those
or one of those positions also is for
another tribal member.
And part of that is because the under
representation that we've had over the
years in various government programs.
And we want to try to be able to help and
ensure that we're hearing the the voices
of as many different people as possible.
And so those are some of the things that
we're we're moving forward.
And we have asked the tribal liaison to
also set up a specific meeting that's not
just for tribal government entities and
individuals,
but for anybody who is a member of a
tribe in Pueblo to be able to join in,
to have a safe space to talk about and
find out more about psilocybin and the
direction that it's going.
And so that we can hear from people the
cultural and historical considerations
that we need to ensure that we're that
we're honoring.
And so we have asked for that.
And our hope is that we see that meetings
getting set up shortly.
However, again,
we do have to work through our tribal
liaison.
And so we'll see as soon as we have
information, we'll put that on out.
And then as far as other information,
some of the things that we've talked
about in some of the previous meetings or
what we really need to do is start honing
in on what are the requirements with
regard to the equity fund.
So for example,
are we looking initially just at things
such as income?
How does geography play into that?
How does membership and otherwise wise
marginalized communities play into that?
How do we help in ensure that there's
access?
And So what we really need to start doing
is start honing that in and making some,
you know,
recommendations so that when it comes
time for that particular set of rules,
we actually are able to say these are the
criteria for individuals to be able to,
you know, to be able to access that fund.
And so, so that's really,
I think the next step.
And,
and we did have some sort of propositions
with regard to that of ensuring things
such as travel and transportation for
individuals,
which I take to also include lodging when
people are travelling.
Methods and ways that the program could
potentially fund for either mobile or,
you know,
for providers to travel into areas rather
than the patients traveling out of areas
to the provider.
So ensuring that we have that,
that's a big part of access as well.
And then some of the other aspects for
once we have locked down and we don't
have this yet,
but once we know how much could
potentially be covered through Medicaid
and through insurance as far As for
billing issues or billing questions.
Once we have that,
then what kind of income requirements
would there be for individuals to be able
to reach or to be able to access the fund?
And we've talked about various levels,
but I think we need to start honing in a
little bit on those levels because that's
kind of the easy part in some ways to be
able to say, if someone's at, for example,
200% of the federal poverty level,
how much will the program then fund the,
you know,
their treatment if they're at at poverty
level or below it,
how much will the program fund?
And sort of setting up a chart with that
to, to really sort of have that.
Is it going to be an all or nothing where,
for example, we say,
if somebody is at 400% of the poverty
level.
And by the way,
these numbers where I'm saying that
percentages are just ones to sort of for
us to starting point to, to discuss.
They're not anything written in stone in
any way, shape or form.
But so for example,
if someone's at 400% of the poverty level,
are we just going to then fund the
treatment at that point?
Or will it be a percentage?
Will it be simply that we turn around and
say and then anyone over that level or
whatever level we decide on,
anyone over that level then you know,
is there no funding allowed or available?
You know,
so it's about those sort of things.
Do we do it graduated or does it become
just a cut off?
If it is graduated or a cut off either
way,
what are those requirements going to be?
And then from there,
one of the things that we'll have to
determine is how much information are
those individuals going to have to
provide showing what their income is?
Do we go with something simple, which is,
by the way,
has happened with many programs where
they simply say the previous year's tax
returns and that helps to determine that
level?
Or do we go into more depth and say we
need to have more information about right
now because people's income levels can
change from one year to the next and
because it's a full year on that
somebody's tax return from the year
before may not reflect where they are now,
whether it is higher or lower.
So these are things that we need to
determine.
Some of it, however,
is going to also be dependent upon the
ability of the program and the resources
the program has to be able to actually
review that.
So for example,
if we said it would be based on income
now and just as a,
a few examples of what they do in certain
other programs that would include things
like what is rent statement so or a,
a rental lease so that we can see how
much is going out for housing,
because there's a very different approach
as well,
looking at it from a standpoint of what
is your income versus what is your
expenses.
And so we have to take that into
consideration as well.
So for example,
we look at what are your last two or
three pay stubs, What are your, you know,
your rental.
Does that then mean that people are not
going to want to submit it and therefore
it might miss out because,
and rightfully so, they say, well,
why does the Department of Health,
why are they being so nosy and want to
see what all my income is and those sort
of things?
So we have to think about some of those
aspects as well because there's also a
certain amount of stigma that is attached
with with many of these questions.
And so do we go with something simpler
like the previous year's tax returns,
knowing that there might be issues and
maybe putting in if somebody's income has
increased,
maybe not worrying about that so much
because of some of the potential stigma
issues.
But if it's decreased,
having an alternate path that someone
then could do these other things that may
be quite frankly more invasive,
but help them in order to be able to
ensure.
So going with something as the first line
being what are your previous year's tax
returns,
simply submit that and then we look at,
but if that is changed and your income
has reduced for whatever reason,
providing what are your last two or three
pay stubs if you don't have them,
do we need a letter that saying,
for example,
you have applied for other benefits,
something like that could be potentially
a part of it.
And so then moving forward,
I'm hoping this is making sense and,
and I would say that our first,
because in some ways it's a little bit
easier,
even though I'm making it sound complex,
is looking at that income level.
And then the next step is looking at
distance and so geography.
And then the next step looking at and,
and again,
these can be mixed up and turned around.
I'd like to hear what other people think.
But then looking at is it an otherwise
marginalized population,
if that makes sense.
And then I'd like to just kind of open it
up at this point or back to you despite
no, I think that was a really good recap.
And I know that some of us might,
this sort of makes sense to me mostly.
And there might be other people out there
who this makes complete,
utter sense because this is the world
that you live in.
And those are the people that I
definitely want to reach out to,
to kind of help with this, right?
So if this if if Dominic is speaking your
language,
you are the person that we need to kind
of help out with this, with this issue.
Because to me at least in this is my own
personal opinion, you know,
this should be available to as many
people as much as possible without any
kind of requirement.
And to me,
my understanding is we have a limited
amount of money that we need to be able
to reach the most amount of people and as
soon as possible given the the timeline
that we're given from MLG.
And so that's kind of the thing.
So this isn't necessarily like we are
trying to gatekeep people from receiving
the medicine.
It's just how are what are the best
practices to be able to get this amount
of money to help the most amount of
people who are really looking forward to
having this access to this medicine?
And what does that look like?
And how are we kind of creating that
environment for that to happen?
So it's not a matter of like,
how are we keeping people out?
It's like,
how can we reach the most people with the
amount of money that's been given?
And being that this is just the start,
if we are effective in doing so,
then this might be able to provide the
data for future applications,
being able to have more money so that we
can reach even more people.
So this is very much just a start.
It doesn't mean that this is going to be,
you know, set in stone.
It might be a little bit this is, this is,
this is the government.
So things might take a while,
but you know, how do we start?
How do we move forward with the amount of
money that we have and reaching the most
amount of people?
And, and it's,
it is just kind of like for some,
for those of you who might know, it's,
it's like,
was it 5 loaves or is it 5 fish,
No2 fish and five loaves?
How are we,
how are we able to get to the most amount
of people with this?
So I think, you know, we're trying to,
we're trying to do some good, but we,
we're, we're limited in some capacity,
but how do we do this?
And so anyone who has input into how to,
how to do this, and I like the idea of,
you know,
if we're looking at last year's taxes or
so forth.
And you know,
I will say that definitely for sure,
I'm in the film industry.
One year you are completely up and then
the next year you're like, OK,
where is how do I apply for SNAP?
So it just can go crazy.
And in this environment and in this
economy,
now we're trying to really figure out how
we're going to help people.
And we're really,
really in this in this place of how we
help.
So this is not about gatekeeping.
It's just about how can we be the most
effective with what we have.
So I don't know if anybody had any things
to start.
Do you want to start, Greg?
OK.
Oh, sure.
I was just curious if there's a way to
partner with this New Mexico to like
leverage their existing platform for
validating like poverty or just, you know,
income issues.
And I know that wouldn't be a wouldn't
catch everything,
but it could reduce the impact on the
department.
The short answer is yes, New Mexico.
Yes, New Mexico.
And so,
but we still have to look at it from a
standpoint as well because the processing
portion that there,
there could be some other indicators and
some other factors to go along with that.
But again,
it also comes down to a situation where
there are going to be people who don't
necessarily want to provide that.
And so we need to just consider that
aspect.
And I would say the other,
the other aspect is then how much,
you know,
are we going to bill or are we going to
consider anything with regard to
potential insurance or Medicaid payments?
Or do we just say, regardless of that,
here's what individuals would be eligible
for and then reduce it based upon what
could potentially be available through
insurance and Medicaid?
Thank you.
This is Hanifa Dial Washington.
I have some questions and some comments.
Let's start with questions in regard to,
I'm not quite sure which subcommittee is
looking at the actual delivery of care in
the care model because we need to have a
baseline of like how much is this going
to cost, right?
So understanding that I think will be
really important to understanding like
how,
what what percentage and what parts of
the care model can be covered,
particularly when you talk about the
medicine itself,
that seems like the the biggest expense
that assistant like Medicaid would not
cover, right.
So really getting clear on, well,
what are the models of care?
How much do that cost?
Are we looking at models that involve
group care?
You know,
so I'm involved with PMHA alliance
supporting the implementation of the
group psilocybin assisted therapy model
for PTSD with doctor Larry Lehman.
And so we're looking at a group model and
it might not exactly match,
but I think there's a lot that could be
learned there with all cost modeling.
And also in Group, a group model, yeah,
it brings costs down.
But also this is the way in which in many
traditional ways the medicine has been
delivered right in Group, in community.
So I,
I think understanding some baseline costs
of what the models are,
whether it's individual care,
group care is really going to help to
inform all of this.
The other thing is I'm curious around
like what is the Department of Health
looking at in terms of what it's willing
to allocate toward the individual or
individuals who would be overseeing this
sort of reviewing process of, of, of,
of applying for,
for care and assistance of the equity
fund?
Because I,
I'm thinking about things from the
backward, like backwards to forwards,
you know, so like, what's the baseline?
What is the care cost?
What is the administration cost for this?
Whatever kind of spitballing so we can
understand the finances a bit more.
And the other thing that I would share is
that when you're we're talking about the
aspects and things that the equity fund
can also cover, I'm curious about like,
you know, non-english speaking, you know,
support and care and translation both in
the written materials and in time,
in real time.
So those are my questions and comments
for now.
Thank you.
Thank you, Hanifa.
And to to sort of cover a few of those
and forgive me if I miss them all because
I have to admit I'm not writing down
notes, but I'll,
I'll start with the as far as from the
administrative side.
So that's a really good question.
And it's actually quite frankly that is
part of what I have to determine and
figure out along with the team here at
the department the amount of funding that
we had as far as position numbers.
What we really have to do is quite
frankly work within our current team.
Now the nice part is that means that it's
not just the psilocybin program,
it's our entire center.
And so as many of you know,
we have a lot of our health educators
have been involved in the process.
They have been working on this.
And we have also on the medical cannabis
side, we have, OK,
they changed the names back when they did
the reorg.
So let me see if I remember this right,
Service representative,
service representative,
I'm not gonna remember all of it.
And in any case,
there are there are customer service
patient oriented staff.
And So what ends up happening is some of
them are going to be tasked with doing
this paperwork side, so to speak.
So the reviewing of applications,
the reviewing of information to ensure
that they have that and we'll be doing
trainings with regard to that.
We've already been reaching out to some
of the other programs, For example,
we work with WIC and some of the other
programs that we have that also do
eligibility requirements with regard to
income.
And so we're already talking about
dependent upon what the requirements will
end up being.
How do we actually help process that?
So what I would really say with regard to
this committee is that's a problem for me
and our team to solve.
Although I appreciate it because it is
part of why I said if we start looking at
requiring all these other items,
that means it takes longer to verify
items,
it takes longer to do it and why certain
other proxies can actually be beneficial.
And it may be that we come up with,
as we're talking with these other aspects
of different agencies like yes,
New Mexico,
where where we come up with four or five
different possible proxies to say here's
what approximate income levels are and
this is what we can do.
So it becomes a lot easier
administratively and so that we're not
spending a lot of time or money in trying
to do that aspect rather than actually
helping people.
And as Dezba kind of mentioned, you know,
the preference would be how do we help as
many people as possible with the limited
funds that we have.
So from that standpoint, administratively,
that's a part that we as a department
have to determine and have to figure out.
The other aspect you brought up is cost
and I and while cost is very important on
it and the,
the aspects of what we're going to end up
seeing covered through Medicaid and
insurance companies is going to be
important.
But the reality is we're not really going
to know that until we have providers
start trying to bill.
We are working with them to try to get
agreements and to try to get
understanding of what codes to use,
what exactly will be covered.
It seems to be tentative agreement that
the therapy sessions prior to and after
the day of administration should be
covered,
but we have to wait and see a little bit.
And So what I think the difference is
what's going to happen is how many people
were going to be able to help cover under
the equity fund.
And there are some other aspects of this
as well.
I,
I don't know how many people have looked
at their behavioral or mental health
insurance lines,
but quite often they'll only cover so
many therapy sessions.
And so we need to think a little bit
about, well,
if somebody really needs to go through
integrative therapy and they need two or
three sessions, you know,
every week and they need to do this for
three months,
will their insurance even cover that?
Or will it only cover a limited amount?
Does the equity program then or the
equity fund then cover the additional?
Because we don't want people to go
through partial treatment.
In some ways that would be worse than not
going through treatment at all.
But just as an example.
And then Greg, you have a, I'm not,
I'm not point.
Yeah, yeah.
Curious the if we can push this through
as a single payment for treatment similar
to cancer treatments where all of the
process is the treatment because it's not
the medical administration point,
it is the therapy leading into it
preparation and the integration.
So if that is the model maybe we can
mitigate some of those multiple payment
things.
No disagreement with you on that at all.
The concern is the administration fees
and separating that on out.
So, but that's a part of why as I say,
I am not an expert when it comes to
Medicaid and insurance.
Absolutely not.
I am not an expert in that regard.
I know about how much my co-pays are and
that's about it.
OK.
I know a little bit more than that,
but the point being is that's why we're
working with HCA and one of the other
board members, Alana Dances,
is actually the director for Medicaid.
And so they've been very helpful with
regard to some of those.
And these are different things that are
being explored.
So, you know, that's a good,
those are good points as far as how we
bring the cost down,
but it's not really going to change what
the requirements are going to end up
being in the long run.
What it's really going to change based on
the cost is how many people were able to
help.
And so,
so that's the one thing I would say as
far as cost model, by the way,
if we're able to get Medicaid and
insurance to cover the therapy aspects
and not on the day of treatment itself or
on the day of administration,
that actually brings the cost including
medication down to under $500 a patient.
But that's what all else being paid for
through those processes.
Some people are going to have,
but their insurance are going to have
co-pays and other aspects.
So we have to take those kinds of things
into consideration as well.
But not necessarily here from the equity
standpoint cuz all that part is going to
change.
And I shouldn't say all it's a big part,
but it doesn't,
it doesn't actually change the aspects of
what requirements for us to be able to
help people do we need to have,
but it's a big part of how many people
will be able to help.
And where that's really going to come
into play, quite frankly,
is in the future with as far as because
remember the equity fund,
this is a one time fund that for the
allocation right now.
So what we need to see what and,
and the possibilities in the future are
how much of it becomes recurring?
Does it become an allocation every year?
Is it something that we have to go back
every single year and say this is how
much money we're going to,
we anticipate needing and all of those
aspects.
And so we don't know those parts yet
either.
So we'll we'll have to wait and see a
little bit on some of that.
But in the meantime, we do have $630,
000 and if we can get the cost of
treatment down to 500.
Oh, and by the way, sorry honey,
I forgot this part.
And for everybody else online,
the 500 that we're talking about is using
a group model.
So individual treatment would end up
being more, of course, or well,
not of course, but I would hope not,
but would end up being more.
But if someone is doing it through a
group model,
that's kind of what we're looking at as
far as a cost.
Some of that is going to depend on what
the licensures look like as the training
and education committee starts actually
allocating the different job duties and
things like that.
And who, for example,
is going to be able to be a facilitator
versus the therapist practitioner role
and those sort of things and what the
modelling will be for that.
So for example,
if it is more one-on-one or you have you
have some sort of supervision therapist
in the building along with someone going
through as a facilitator with an
individual on a one-on-one sort of
situation,
the cost is going to be more a group
setting much less.
And so we have to look at that.
And that's another consideration.
I personally,
and this is me speaking as me not from
the department at this moment,
would be what would we want to turn
around and say for the equity fund that
it needs to be?
Then if you're going to be eligible for
it,
you would have to do a group setting
because there are many patients who are
going to say,
I don't want to be in a big group,
I don't want to be in a small group.
And so then are there going to be
restrictions on that?
And from a healthcare standpoint,
that really shouldn't be the case.
That's however,
going to change how many people can be
helped with this.
And so does that even become a factor
with regard to it?
And so those are some of the other
considerations.
And it's why in some ways,
I kind of say from a,
a more of an ease standpoint,
if we look at income requirements to
start,
that kind of gives us a little bit of
progress with while these other questions
are still waiting to be answered.
Does that help?
I hope that helps.
And can you tell I've been thinking about
this a lot.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, Dominic,
and it's really helpful.
And I think there's, you know,
sometimes when I've been talking with you
does around like the importance of the
cross pollination of the subcommittees
because I immediately think about the
care model will need to be different for
the different conditions, right?
Like you're not going to do a group model
at end of life.
So you would need,
so if you if you need support and you
want to apply for it in the life care,
like it can't be a group model.
So is it about a certain percentage of
the care, et cetera.
Or if you're in a group model,
it covers this much.
If you do individual, it covers that much.
So yeah,
but I really clearly you've been thinking
about this a lot and my mind thinks I can
think about systems.
And so when it comes to like, OK,
this committee and what this committee
can, you know, support and touch on,
it's hard for me to sometimes separate
the 2.
So thank you.
I also just before I forget,
we have already been approached by some
foundations that also are interested and
and they've kind of said, well,
how do we utilize some of these funds
that we have or may have in the future.
And some of the things we've said is some
things that have come up in some of these
committees have been very clear at that
they are needs,
but not necessarily things that we would
be able to cover for a variety of reasons
such as how much could we help cover
families, for example,
during end of life and the additional
care that they need.
We may not be able to do that through the
program.
And if not,
it could be that there's supplemental
funds available through some of these
other foundations.
And we try to figure out a streamlined
way for people to do applications so that
quite frankly they're not spending 10
hours filling out application after
application after application.
And so that's something else that we've,
we've also had some conversations with
those foundations and one in particular.
But to say, OK,
how could this potentially help?
And they have to make their own decisions
on whether that's something they want to
do or not.
But those are some other areas we're
looking at because even though it may not
be something we could do through the
department,
it may be something that we can help with
assistance in those other resources.
Oh,
and the other part you asked is as far as
translation.
Our public health offices actually have
translation services that are available
and we would also be linking into those
to be able to provide it for patients who
need them.
OK, Sorry, Dominic,
you raised a couple of things that just
made me think about it.
I wanted to just for anyone not doing any
kind of math and I know these are not the
actual numbers that we're using and I do
want to clarify the 500,
I know you said it was for group,
but just doing the math on $630,000,
if we if each treatment per person is $10,
000, it's 63 people.
And if we were to do a group model and
that was and we were able to allocate
$500 per person for the group model,
then we can reach 1260 people.
So I'm not saying that those are actual
numbers that,
but I'm just kind of throwing out a
little bit of math.
You know, an individual treatment at $10,
000 cost.
And this is considering all the the
testing of the facilitator pay and just
just the whole streamline from from
propagation to to facilitator to the
person to the cost of the treatment
itself to the service and then also post
treatment.
If it was anyway around $10,
000 at 63 people.
And again, 500 is for like a group model.
And just one thing that before I hand the
mic back to Dominic or anyone else who
has a question or comment,
it also I think depends on the coding for
what is being able to be provided with
the insurance and who's able to do what.
Because at this point,
we're still was it a schedule 1.
So I don't know if that takes a play into
it as to what is going to be able to be
built.
And I think that might be something that
needs to be looked at in terms of like
how where that money is going to go
because I feel like it might,
this is just my opinion.
So I want clarification on that is if
it's going to go to therapy that might be
easier to justify for the funding or is
there any kind of because it is
specifically for the psilocybin that it's
OK.
So I just don't know if like coding for
insurance or anything like else like that
would come into play.
And then also if you had already been
toying with numbers, Dominic,
where exactly did the 500 come from or if
that was just an example number?
So those two questions,
the coding and the $500, that's great.
And actually the 500 is based on if
Medicaid and insurance companies pay for
the therapy.
So we would be looking at just the day of
administration.
So we're talking in that point of
anywhere really from 8 to 10 hours worth
of facilitator and like a a practitioner,
so a licensed counselor type physician,
that sort of aspect of it.
And again,
some of it's going to depend on what the
insurance companies,
the Medicaid would cover.
And so that's where that actually that
comes in and the cost of the medication
itself.
So that's what factors into that 500.
And again,
depending on what exactly gets covered,
that could either be a little more or a
little less.
But as Hanifa kind of said,
we kind of need to have a little bit of a
starting point.
And so this gives us a little bit of an
idea.
The reality is it'll probably be
somewhere in between, you know,
and especially if with the billing and
the coding were able to get all of the
therapy aspects covered with the
potential exception of co-pays that may
add some to it.
For example.
And again,
depending on how many sessions
individuals need,
and we've had those conversations and
some of the other committees that one
person might need only one or two
preparatory sessions,
someone else might need four or five or
even more.
And so that also is going to come into
play.
So I,
I wouldn't want us to focus on exactly
how much is each session going to cost
with the coverage of Medicaid and
insurance.
We really just need to look at it from a
standpoint, at least from this committee.
We're going to try to explore all of
those other ways for things to get paid,
and we're going to continue to do that no
matter what else is going on.
But with the money that we do have,
how do we figure out to disperse it in a
way that's going to be as equitable as we
can and realizing that it might be that
we're able to help only 63 people?
Or we might be able to hit it might be
able to help more than 1000 with the
funds that we have right now.
And our goal is to going to be of course
to help as many people as possible.
But until we start having the billing
work and be successful,
we're not going to fully now because
there's a lot of a lot of questions out
there right now of modeling it for
example,
on some of the codes that are utilized or
similar codes utilized for like ketamine
treatment, for example,
or are there other codes that could be
utilized?
The doing it as a single event sort of
payment is one of the other ones that
we've been looking at.
And we're not the only ones.
There are several organizations around
the country that are trying to figure
this out.
So it's not like we're, you know,
we're the only ones,
nor are we always necessarily going to be
the ones who will figure it out.
Our hope is that some of the folks who
are experts will be able to make some of
those determinations and be able to help
us.
And that especially includes HCA itself.
So I hope that helps.
But that's a part of why I kind of say
too,
is if we can start figuring out what the
criteria are,
then we can start looking at it.
And as we get more information on what is
going to be covered through insurance,
Medicaid or not covered at all.
Because if we don't have any coverage at
all on it, you know,
the treatment cost could be anywhere from
2500 and up.
And so that's going to then greatly limit
how many people were able to help.
But is that going to change from a
standpoint of what people can really
afford?
If you can't even afford, you know,
to go in to see your therapist once,
then does it matter if you have to go see
them once or 10 times?
We have to figure a way on how we can
help those individuals the most and how
we can cover it.
So at least best as we can with the
resources we have.
And and I'd rather help 50 people than
help no one.
Thank you for further explaining that a
little bit, Dominic, appreciate it.
Because that's kind of just why I wanted
to just like make sure that we kind of
understand wrapping our heads around,
you know, like we're,
we are trying to figure out baseline cost
and I think that there are some metrics
we need to understand, but it's also just,
you know, some of us might think $630,
000 is a lot.
I,
I'm tend to be one of those people and
some of us know exactly how much,
how little that can actually be and what
we're dealing with when it,
when it comes to, you know, helping and,
and figuring out the cost of these things
because it, it does add up.
You know, this,
it adds up from propagation to light the
testing, etcetera.
And testing.
I feel like it's going to be one of the
expenses.
And if you've been in the propagation.
And we also had a rules meeting this past
Friday, I believe.
So there's a lot going on and we're
trying to figure it all out.
And so these are not just like isolated
instances.
We are gonna start trying to connect
everything together,
but in the capacity that we can
understand something as isolated.
You know,
for those of you who are math nerds,
you'll know it's like you you ignore
gravity or you ignore certain things in
order to actually do the equation because
given the circumstances,
there are a number of variables.
So we're trying to eliminate some of
those variables in order to be able to
kind of move forward with the process.
So yeah,
I don't know if there's anybody else who
might have a comment or a question that
is online at this point.
So we've actually had a couple of
comments online,
one of them from Kathy just talking about,
you know, using for example,
what hospitals have for their charity or
scale applications and utilizing some
items from that with regard to income
versus expense versus dependents and
etcetera.
And yes, I agree on that.
And then another step for individuals who
are not indigent patients,
considering our process that when they
have insurance,
the provider accepts only the insurance
payment as payment in full,
limiting any balance billing for the
patients.
So in other words,
they essentially write off whatever the
balance may be.
And yes,
that's something that we've also kind of
talked about as well.
And then we have from Soma had mentioned
that their research supporting the
benefit of group therapy and locum group
psilocybin assisted therapy.
And that also is some of the research
that actually Hanif has been involved
with you know and Doctor Larry Lehman
over at U&M.
And so, yes,
we are looking at that as well.
And and some are mentioning the HOPE
pilot study with cancers,
cancer patients and yay U&M.
So yeah,
so that the those are all good points.
And and it's a part of why we're looking
at those models because if they can be
helpful,
then we want to make sure that they're
available.
But again,
it comes down to something that quite
frankly the whichever model works for a
patient is really between the patient and
the provider.
So we don't want to limit too much on
saying, hey,
if you can't afford something,
we're going to force you to do a
treatment that you don't think is the
best one for you and that your provider
doesn't think is best for you.
So just to be clear,
we are not advocating for treatment
restrictions, so to speak.
So, you know,
so those are different things.
And and here's the other aspect, yes,
we are going to start with whatever our
criteria end up being in the beginning,
I will guarantee we will be modifying it
as things move forward,
especially as we develop and we determine
different needs that there are in the
state and different populations that are
going to need it.
So to me, I feel like,
and maybe you have already stated this,
Dominic, but I like redundancy.
What specific aspect of figuring out like
the first point would be helpful for a
potential recommendation from the board
to the to the DoH, Meaning, you know,
we land on somewhere to start it.
OK, we're going to,
we're going to start at 200% poverty
level.
That's like that's where our starting
point of,
of this piece of the puzzle we're going
to be.
Is that something that's a reasonable
request or like that's,
that's what maybe we can come out of
What's happening here today is just like
we need to start,
we're going to start at 200% of poverty
level, right?
And I would say the question the,
the next question,
once we go with what it, what percentage,
for example, the next question would be,
does it become an all or nothing?
So if someone is at 200% poverty level or
lower,
do we simply say that then the treatments
will be covered through the equity fund.
So the payments come out of the equity
fund domain or does it become something
that is a scale where it is percentage.
So for example, at 200 percent,
100% of the treatments are covered
through the equity fund.
At 300 percent,
is it 75% of the cost of the treatments
at 400%, is it 50%?
You know those kind that that I would say
are what we really need from a starting
basis.
And I would say whatever we do decide
here or whatever the recommendation is
here,
it also be something that be as tentative
at this point and be a starting place.
Because as we do get more information
those may adjust up and down.
And so we don't take it as the
recommendation is boom and this is where
it is.
But as we find out more information over
the next several months about how much
will insurance potentially cover and we
get either more assurances or we get flat
out told, Yep,
it's not going to get covered,
that as we know that information,
we'd be prepared to adjust those.
But if we at least have a starting basis
that way we can start planning some of
the other aspects such as transportation
planning.
What other aspects could we potentially
cover?
How do we cover not just that,
but also what populations and are is
there a way where we say, for example,
that OK,
we started at 200% poverty level for the
general public.
However,
if someone is a member of a Native
American tribe or Pueblo, we, you know,
increase that to 300%.
Are there other considerations we do for
that?
If someone is, for example,
experiencing homelessness,
regardless of what their tax returns say
last year,
it's automatically we will cover their
payments.
You know,
start looking at those kinds of
exceptions and the other ways to ensure
we have equity across the board with
different populations.
Does that help?
Oh, Hanifa has.
Oh yeah.
And while while we're letting Hanifa
about a comment,
if there's anybody who already has one of
these models that they'd like to propose
and suggest,
you can probably do that in the comment
at this point, we can look at that.
Because I know that I one pops up to mind,
you know,
because I actually honestly have to do
these all the time.
You know, I have to submit.
I'm definitely do not make more than a
certain amount of money and I have to
kind of find out and gauge myself,
you know,
how much do I feel like this program can
provide for me and for whatever it is
that we're doing?
So we'll let Hanifa comment.
Thank you.
I just have two questions.
One is around the equity fund and it's
timeline.
So you mentioned that it's only for,
it's only a one time occurring thing.
Is that until the money is then gone or
is it based on a date?
And then also in terms of the
recommendations coming from this
committee,
is there a desired timeline of when we
want to have those forth for review?
So the funding currently that has been
allocated is through to the end of FY20 7.
So we're currently currently in FY20 6.
And so this gives us, I'm sorry,
FY20 8 is where it ends.
So this essentially gives us a year and a
half from when we start the program.
So if our goal is for patients to be seen
in December of 26,
that is halfway through FY20 7 and now it
becomes confusing state fiscal year
versus calendar year.
But and so essentially from that point
moving forward we will have a year and a
half to utilize that funds.
Now the legislature could allocate
additional funding during the next
legislative cycle and if that happens
then the fund will continue moving
forward.
The original bill had requested $1
million per year of what's called non
reverting funds.
That means that at the end of the fiscal
year the funds do not return back to the
general fund for the state,
but stay with the whatever program they
are in and can be used continually.
The fund is non reverting,
but the way it was allocated this year
was through allocations from different
representatives and state senators for
this money And it goes,
it's what was called the New Mexico
Growth Fund where they are able to
allocate funds to specific projects.
And so it came through there.
So it's a little bit different this this
time around,
but the hope is in the future.
And the original intent was that it
become a recurring allocation.
Whether that happens or not,
we have to wait for the legislature.
So that answer,
I hope that answers that question.
And by the way,
there's still some question about because
it was,
even though it was done through the
growth fund,
because the fund itself is a is a non
reverting fund,
whether we would still have access to it
after the year and a half and if the
monies would not revert.
And that's a question really for the
legislative Finance Committee and we'll
see what happens on that.
We've asked and we'll see what the final
response is,
but at this point the way we're operating
on it is that the funds will be good for
that year and a half from when we start
seeing patients for that next year and a
half does that.
I hope that helps and then I apologize.
What was the other question?
I was just like when should this
committee be putting forward
recommendations on the equity?
So what I would recommend for the
committee is to have the recommendations
ready by the end of summer.
And the reason for that is because we
still have to go through the rule process,
but that will give a couple of months to
go through that rule process and still be
there in advance of the first patients in
December.
So not yet having a firm date.
I would say end of summer yeah,
like maybe I would say towards the end of
August,
middle to end of August middle was
probably be a little better, but you know,
it's was it Leo season?
Yes, right, right, right.
When school starts back.
How's that sound?
Can I do yeah,
question for I have a small list,
but is the equity fund state or federal
Baptist state funds?
It's state that OK,
So that means we have more flexibility
making payments for the actual medicine
because I was curious if like producers
like could offer like in kind for these
specific things just but if it was
federal that like like they wouldn't be
able to get paid, you know,
so like that was, you know, and Greg,
that's a great point.
And and it's part of why, you know,
when we look at this,
if insurance is able to cover the other
aspects, the therapeutic side,
then the equity fund,
especially for individuals who otherwise
would not be able to afford it,
that money can come out of the equity
fund.
And the really good part about it is once
we have the the producers and their
providers are actually permitted,
we actually can make the payments
directly to them.
This is the background part.
So if I know you like this part,
because the problem is to be able to
actually cut a check from the state to go
to an individual,
that individual has to be entered into
and do AW2 form for our W9 form for what
is called the share system,
which is the state financial system.
That means that every patient would have
to then turn around and do AW9 form if we
were to pay the patients directly.
But the way we would set it on up is to
pay the providers and in this case for
the cultivators or producers be able to
pay them directly.
That limits them from an administrative
standpoint.
Instead of having to pay 1000 people,
we maybe only have to pay 102 hundred
depending how many providers we have,
right?
And if you have direct sales to produce
from the producers to the providers and
the providers are the ones actually
making that transaction that you can
reduce it even further.
I don't think there's an answer for this
question,
but I just wanted to put it into the
world.
So what do we do with applicants for the
program who are obviously have treatment
resistant conditions where they may not
have had the economic capacity or will to
seek previous psychological care,
therefore they don't have a record of
medical treatment proving treatment
resistant conditions.
I don't think we need an answer for that
today.
And some of that is actually going to be
the requirements for the conditions
themselves.
And so that actually goes under the
really would go under the patient
qualification committee.
And in that case the the main 1 is really
the treatment resistant depression.
The others don't actually have
necessarily from a statutory standpoint
have those those particular restrictions.
And the main reason is because it is
named in statute as treatment resistant
depression.
So then you have to determine well,
how do we know it's treatment resistant?
But again that is up to the patient
qualification committee and they've been
working on that part as you know.
Yeah, yeah.
And I think so from the bundled payments
or the episode based payment model,
it there is definitely like leaning
towards like I know Doctor Fatemi has
treatment resistant first framework
already established.
Then we put forward what those payment
models tend to be more open to that type.
So I'm just thinking about putting,
but yeah,
I think we have a lot more to fit too.
Are there any comments from the?
So we do have a couple of comments in the
chat just from Kathy.
It was just,
it's a basic question about how
psilocybin is assessed and if there's a
different rating or severity level to
help determine patients who have the
greatest need.
And the short answer on that is yes,
they can be assessed,
but there's going to be different levels
because they're vastly different
conditions.
So for example,
it's it would be very difficult to equate
need with regard to end of life with need
for APTSD for example.
But that is something that we could
potentially explore.
And then from SOMA,
will the agencies or people receiving the
funding be documenting and research based
And so that it if we're expecting success
more likely to receive funding again at
the same or high higher levels.
And again, the short answer is that yes,
there'll be data collected,
but it hasn't been determined yet how
much data and looking evaluation of not
just the program,
but outcomes for the patients has to be
determined and that has not yet been
determined.
And the research and continuous
improvement, wait,
is it continuous quality improvement
research And it is continuous the
research and right racing research and
continuous improvement is looking at some
of those aspects of it.
And yes, the more we talk about this,
the more like different aspects there are
to that have to be considered.
And it's a part of why I kind of say at
this point,
we sort of need to start somewhere
because there are going to be all of
these different things and we can keep
talking about all of them for the next 5
years,
but we're going to have to start
somewhere.
And then as things also move forward and
be considerate about it and, you know,
thoughtful about it.
But then as things move forward,
know that we're going to need to adjust
things.
Because if there's anyone who's figured
out any way to truly be equitable all the
time,
I'd like to know who they are because we
need them.
I always like to think or have a
conversation with my kid.
It's like fair doesn't mean equal.
Let's keep that in mind.
So I did,
I did look at the Be Well newmexico.com.
If anyone wants to go there,
it's forward answers/ FPL dash chart/ Be
Well newmexico.
com/answers/FPL dash chart/ And so just
for example,
this is the kind of thing that Dominic is
looking at as far as like a chart and
from where to start.
I don't think that this is necessarily
the chart we need to look at,
but it's something that we're being asked
to decide if what the percentage level
that we're going to start looking at to
do that scaling.
This one does not have a scaling chart
and I'm not sure where to get one at this
point just yet,
but it is what the percentage chart,
if anyone's not familiar with that is if
you are at 200%,
if there's like the middle line,
if anyone's already on that chart,
200% federal poverty line for an
individual or for a family of two family
of 3.
Based on that chart,
how much of the treatment cost will that
person or that family be able to get
their their treatment covered?
Is it 100% of the treatment?
Is it 75?
Is it half and so forth.
So based on those guidelines,
if you fall with if you are making so
that's this isn't quite necessarily the
chart, but it looks like that.
So if you're falling in that particular
place, like if you say you make 30,
000 dollars, 50,000 dollars, $60,
000 or however much it needs to live in
New Santa Fe, NM.
And I'm going to be facetious.
If you are making $600,
000 to be able to live in New Mexico,
will your treatment be able to be 100%
covered,
only half at that rate and what that
looks like.
So those that's the real question that
we're being asked for a recommendation is
what does that scale look like?
And depending on how much if you're
making.
And for some of us, like I said,
where I'm in the film industry,
I could be making a lot of money
depending on if the films are doing
really well here in New Mexico or
currently,
like now I am struggling to figure out
how to get paycheck to paycheck then pay
my rent.
So if we're looking at how much I say was
made last year, you know,
I would probably maybe whatever.
But this year I'm really struggling and
really need help.
Are we looking at last year's taxes and
last year's income?
Are we looking at this year?
And maybe it's both,
Maybe it's whichever is the lesser the
lesser 1 and that's the one we're going
to go with.
But then also,
how much of that treatment cost is it
going to be?
And if I'm only making $50,000 a year,
we all know what $2000 rent,
you're basically at poverty level or
below.
So you know,
how much of that treatment is going to be
covered.
And I would hope that it would be 100%.
I would hope that we would be able to
cover 100% of that treatment cost if I
really, really needed it,
if I had a really horrible anxiety or
depression or some sort of thing based on
the conditions that we're providing for
the, the rules, you know, patient has $50,
000, you know,
this particular year for some people,
that's a lot.
Maybe that's the most if you've ever made
in your life.
But for living in Santa Fe,
that's nothing or, you know,
I don't want to put that on people,
but you know,
the cost of living here is just so high.
But if you're in Espanola,
that might be different, right?
So we're kind of also having to look at
those things based on the, the area,
the demographics, the financial area,
the county.
What does that look like?
So that's,
I think that's also the other question
too, that I'm, I'm getting from Dominic.
Is it only going to be based on income
and or is it also going to be based on
where you're at?
Because the cost of living in Santa Fe is
much higher than it is in Espanola,
but it's actually also rising in Espanola,
but that'll be different than it is in
Farmington.
So are we going to be looking at some of
these things who, who is eligible, who is,
who is need based?
And we're going to have to kind of come
up with a chart,
a scale that we're looking at.
And this is just a place to start.
This isn't what's going to be forward
into the future.
We can have these things adjusted.
We could look at these things because
another one of these,
what I put down on my notes here is the
add-ons that we can look at later,
which is the accessibility for
translators.
Someone also mentioned child care,
elder care, you know,
maybe maybe they might be able to afford
the the treatment itself, but you know,
you're a single parent and you're also
taking care of your elder parent and
you're going to need a little bit more
help than just paying just for the
treatment.
So these are other considerations,
but the first starting point is finding
out a place to start with the chart and
how much of the poverty line and also
then tweaking it to this,
the socioeconomic like where you're at
different counties to different counties.
I think Los Alamos,
Santa Fe are the are the highest cost of
living.
I'm not sure if there's any other ones.
But then I've also, you know,
Albuquerque and Las Cruces area,
I'm not sure which what is what is Las
Cruces?
What county is that?
Dona Ana?
So those are all going to be different.
And each of those has their own little
rural areas within it too.
So I think the the starting point though
is the chart.
Anyone.
So yeah,
is there anybody who has an idea of where
they think that this should start?
And Kathy had said sounds like creating a
chart where there are different prices
for different cities would cause a lot of
problems.
Is that how it's done with medical
cannabis?
Might be easier to follow a previously
accepted or successful charge scale,
not creating different price for various
cities.
And so Kathy, just to let you know,
we actually don't have this with regard
to medical cannabis at all.
The the analogy that we did have for
medical cannabis in the past was before
the Cannabis Regulation Act was passed in
2001,
patients could apply for a permit to grow
their own cannabis and at that time,
and that changed over the years.
Originally it was if they were,
if an individual was at 200% of the
poverty level or less than they had no
fee.
We then expanded that to 400% of the
poverty level or less than there was no
fee.
And by the way,
the fee for that was only $30 a year.
So it wasn't an exorbitant fund.
But again,
when someone's at that level of that,
that percentage of the poverty level,
every little bit helps.
So we wanted to ensure that was there.
And as far As for qualifications for it,
we were really very,
very permissible on that.
People really just had to sign an
affidavit saying that they made that,
that they were at that level.
And part of that was because quite
frankly,
at that time we were still all paper
applications.
It would take weeks to go through and
improve everything.
And we didn't have the resources to be
able to turn around and say we're going
to now look into everybody's, you know,
income levels.
So submit it.
And so it really from that, that regard,
it was actually very permissible.
But I think on this side,
because we are actually taking funds
because in that case it was just they
didn't have to pay a fee.
In this case,
we're taking funds and dispersing them.
We are going to have to have
documentation.
So that was sort of a little bit of a
difference.
I do also think that it would be very
difficult to do it based upon different
counties and cities,
although there is huge amount of
variation.
So it may be something where we might be
able to figure out sort of a,
a separate sort of process where
individuals could actually then turn
around and say, however,
I live in these areas and there would be
need,
but that would be extraordinarily
draining from a resource standpoint and
be very difficult to do so.
So that's a part of why it's not,
as I mentioned before,
if anybody has a really good way of doing
equity, that would be great.
But reality is we have to think about
those limitations as well.
Now we might be able to do something
different based upon regions or within
counties,
but doing more than that would be
extraordinarily problematic and just from
a a sheer scale standpoint.
So hopefully we have a different chart
and this is a little bit more has has
better numbers.
The one that I said before,
it is from the hca.newmexico.
gov and it is a scale and this is more
representative of the percentage of the
poverty line that we're looking at.
So if anyone is able to look at that
chart that is going to be in the chat.
It does say that the poverty line for a
household of 1 is at 200%.
The poverty line is $31,920.00.
So based on that, and again,
the caveat is that we all know that the
poverty line is a little crazy.
It's that's, that's nothing.
But if we were to start at the poverty
line, 200% of the poverty line,
meaning that if we were to say that our
rules and regulations would cover for,
as an example, 100% of treatments,
if you were at that threshold or below.
So if you were to apply and you were able
to prove that you are at 200% poverty
level or below,
then you would get 100% of the treatment
taken care of.
And this is for the treatment itself.
And would that be covering all sessions?
Is that what we're asking or is that just
a little too far ahead?
Is this just,
is it for the treatment itself or would
it be also including the full gamut Or we
could say that it covers the full
treatment itself and that could be
anywhere from three sessions,
which would be a survey intake and then
the treatment itself and then an
integration session.
So it'd be at least AABC model or it
could be, you know,
depending on how many sessions that a
person needed.
And this is where I think you mentioned
earlier,
if anyone wasn't here in the meeting
earlier was we don't know how many
sessions a person might need per
treatment.
And so,
and then we're also kind of coming up
with, with these definitions,
what exactly is a treatment?
Is that in including intake treatment
itself and then integration and how many
of those sessions And that's for an
individual versus group bug in we're
looking at starting lines,
we're looking at a place to start.
And my example is 200% poverty level at
$31,000 and 100% treatment coverage.
So, oh, that one's just super quiet here.
Can, can, yeah.
OK.
So it's a good question.
And I actually would say that we're going
to have to have maximums essentially of
what can be covered.
So for example, I mean,
I've been in therapy for many, many, many,
many years,
will probably always be in therapy
because my personal belief is that
therapy is very helpful for people to be
able to go through and helps people
center themselves and be more mindful.
And so that's there.
So if we have another individual or even
if say it was myself,
how long would the program cover that
therapy even though it's not necessarily
focused on the psilocybin.
And so I think we're going to end up
having to determine what are the maximum
number of sessions to be covered and all
of that.
And and I don't think we're there yet to
make that determination because some of
that is going to depend on what comes out
of the patient qualification and dosage
and administration committees.
What I would say is to focus at this
point on how much as far as what levels
would be we'd be willing to be able to
cover as far as the poverty levels and
then some of the other ancillary things
we talked about.
And then once again,
that maximum amount of how many sessions
would be covered from from that
standpoint,
we can determine that in a little while
as those other committees start making
the determination of how many sessions
are going to are reasonable to be covered,
because we want to make sure that we're
doing this in a reasonable way.
And it's not going to necessarily work
for everyone.
The best way for that is through words
that I'm not supposed to say.
So I won't say them single payer.
So, you know,
we do have those sort of things that that
sort of move forward,
but I would say looking at it from the
standpoint.
And so we have right now.
Is there anyone who's objecting?
Sorry,
but I'm going to take this part since you
proposed it.
You know,
where we say we start with 200% of the
poverty level that then that through the
equity fund we would be looking at paying
for that treatment.
Is there any objection to that?
I'm seeing head nods of no objection.
Anybody online have an objection to it?
Nobody objecting in the chat.
So that's our starting point, I would say.
So we start off with the 200% on that.
Do I hear 300%?
Sorry, 500%.
Well, I mean, if,
if therapy is if therapy is preventative
care and everybody should be in therapy
when they're feeling good so that when
they have prices,
they have a support system, then, yeah,
just like hopefully it's all covered
under their insurance for if if somebody
is below the poverty line,
they should hopefully already have access
to Medicaid, which covers so much already.
What I was curious about was if you know
what that one is gone.
It's gone.
So here's my next question then.
So what sort of level should we look at
now as far as are we going to say that
it's 200% poverty and anything below that,
you know,
would be covered with the understanding
of we will eventually have maximums and
things like that to put into place,
Do we then turn around and say what would
be the next level?
So is it the 200% and below it's covered
and then over 200% nothing's covered?
Or do we say, what's that next step?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, do we go in 100% or do we say,
and this is I think where that chart that
that we shared is actually helpful
because if you look at it and for those
who are able to see it, it, you know,
if you look at it when you hit 200% of
poverty level, sorry,
I'm going back to it.
You know that 200 percent is 31,
920 for a family size of 1.
And then when you get to 300%,
that becomes 47,
880 and then 400 percent is 63,840.
So is it something that we want to go and
that the recommendation should be about
going up in increments of 100% or going
up in increments of 50% or 25%?
And so, you know, and then if So,
what are the percentages of payment that
would occur at that point?
And so for those who are not able to look
at the chart, we do have again, 200,
000% of poverty level is $31,
920 annual income.
And at 300%, we have $47,880.
And this is for an individual,
this is not for families,
it's just all individual.
And so we're looking at those and for
400%, just to get for perspective,
the individual would be making 63,840.
I believe that's an 8, yes, 840.
So the question being asked is,
are we jumping full 100% to these
different income levels and how much of
the treatment cost would then be covered?
So for instance,
if we decided to jump 100% and that would
bring it as an individual making $47,
880 or below between,
between the 200 threshold, right?
So 31,921,
all you math nerds I know are just loving
this and one cent, right?
So between that level and the full 300,
would we then be able to,
with the rules and regulations of the
medical psilocybin advisory regulations
cover 75% of the treatment.
Those are the scales that we're looking
at.
And at 400%,
would we then cover half of the cost of
the treatment.
So that's the next proposal.
And those are the levels that the
Department of Health is looking for as a
recommendation from the community to say,
yes,
these individuals making this amount of
money,
I think that we should be able to help
them at this rate and at this cost if
they are at this level.
So again,
this is not necessarily like a
gatekeeping.
This is also just being able to figure
out how do we allocate the limited number
of funds that we have and be able to help
most number of people that we can.
So we have Hanifa,
who has a question or did you want to
answer something?
Hey,
we had in the chat we just had Kathy that
asked if the money is just available for
those who do not have insurance and the
response is no,
this is actually for anyone because we
also do not know if insurance will
actually cover it.
While we've gotten tentatives,
it should we do not yet have a definitive
yes.
My question was around, oh,
so like should we be thinking about what
the scale of the parameters are like as
good?
Would we just keep going up?
Are we saying between 200 and 500?
Are we just going to keep like what's the
end cap of what we're saying?
Because then I think that'll help
determine like is it an additional 50 or
100 or whatever?
Does that make sense?
That question makes sense.
Yes, it does.
And that's actually a part of what what
we're kind of asking.
So like in my original example,
I said do we do it where like say,
and again,
this is not real numbers or
recommendation, but say at 300%,
we say then it's 75% is covered, at 400%,
it's 50% is covered.
And then after that,
do we go to 25% at 500 or do we say,
you know what, at that point,
individuals should be making enough money.
And so that's really where the question
comes in, what level do we go to on that?
And then how would that scale sort of
work?
And if we do it, for example, as,
and Greg, correct me if I'm wrong,
you were trying to say at 25%,
so like doing from 200 to 225 and that
sort of a thing.
I, I,
or if it was just being thrown out as a
possibility, you know, again,
that's a possibility.
And all we need to know at that point or
from a recommendation standpoint is,
you know,
what sort of what would we then
anticipate people to be paying as far as
a percentage?
I mean,
as somebody who recently found
theirselves without an income and was
making less than $60,000 a year,
like I don't think that I could afford
$500.00 for therapy.
I could probably afford 100 bucks,
you know, so, so to speak.
So like whatever incremental thing makes
sense.
What I remember from earlier that I
wanted to bring up is utilizing
standardized deductions to kind of bucket
the cost.
And honestly,
like if somebody's asking for help,
just to help, like, I mean,
if we have the money and,
and if we blow the budget,
that's a good thing.
Like we need to spend every dime of this
and it needs to get to people and it I
mean, like, honestly,
the money is going to go to support the
infrastructure of the industry.
It's going to be going to the people
providing care and providing the
infrastructure for that care.
So if this money goes out to support the
development of the industry and therefore
creating a care model that we can show
data has success rate by aligning
patients with the proper provider
networks and provider like pipelines,
then we can yeah, anyways,
collect that data and get more money.
Because I think we could easily like
double or triple this fund just to make
sure that I think I.
What I'm hearing you saying is, you know,
even if for instance, it turns out that,
you know,
we come up with a model and we do say go
on the lower end of helping people like
the quantity,
we do go more towards the lower end like
63.
But we're able to provide the data for
exactly how we were able to do XY and Z,
having that data for how this model
worked and how well we use the funds.
And that would be in itself a good use of
the funds even if we weren't able to hit,
you know, a certain lot of people.
And then some kind of,
I don't know how else to describe it,
but you know, but just being able to, to,
to document the pathway from, you know,
how well we use this fund.
I'd love to hear the money people's side
of that answer.
I just want to say one more thing, please.
Let's just clarify what I was trying to
say before.
This is, honey, if I get it,
which is if we're saying at the low,
we're saying the low end is 200% below
the poverty level.
What are we saying?
The cap is?
Is it what is that number?
Like that's what?
And then we can determine whatever steps
in between get what percentage.
But I'm just curious, like,
what are people's thoughts on how much
money can you be making where like we
stop providing equity support and,
and honey,
if I think that's a great question and,
and it's a part of what, you know,
I'd like to hear too, because you know,
different people it and depending on
what's happening with within their lives,
that may be very much of a different,
you know,
a different amount for different things
going on.
And that's a part of why when we talk
about things as far as income coming in
and expenses can also be a part of that
equation.
It could potentially be problematic.
So for example,
you might have someone who has a high
income, but if they're caring,
even if they're not claimed in their
household,
caring for an elderly parent or anything
else for reasons such as insurance or
other reasons,
then you might actually have,
they don't have the income,
even though it may appear, you know,
that they have it.
Or I'm sorry, they don't have the,
the funds to be able to pay for the
treatment,
even though it may appear that way.
So,
but that's what we have to make a
reasonable assumption.
And So what is that level?
Is that level 400% of poverty level?
Is that 500% poverty level?
I mean, and again, looking at the chart,
it doesn't go up to 500%, but it's at 63,
840 is 400% of the poverty level.
And if we are able to get the cost down
to about $500.
00 for with everything else being covered
either through Medicaid or insurance,
is that a reasonable amount to say?
You know,
that's kind of the upper limit on that at
that point.
And again,
that's for a single individual to give
everyone an idea, for a family of four,
400 percent is 132,000.
Wow.
And I happen to pick the one that's even
at 132,000.
So you know that just as an example,
we're not, we're, you know, this chart,
while we would look at the percentage,
it would be based upon what their family
household level is.
So,
so those are some of the other aspects.
And then as far as trying to spend as
much of it as possible for people, yes,
it would be what the program's goal would
be is to be able to get treatment to as
many people as possible.
There are a couple of questions in the
chat that actually do fit along with that
and this was from Kathy as a thought that
if we get everyone used to the DoH paying
100% of the treatment and then we are not
able to get additional funds into the
equity fund.
Do people then end up going into a shock
because they then suddenly regardless of
anything have to pay full amount the next
year and going forward.
So is it a good idea to have patients
regardless pay some portion of the
treatment charges?
So that's a consideration.
And then from SOMA,
I think it's important to distinguish
whether regular insurance or Medicaid can
cover the pre and post integration
therapy and just just not the medication
session.
And so the answer on that is we still
don't know.
We've gotten indications they'll cover it,
but there's no determined yes on that.
And part of it is where some of the
concern has come in is that because if it
is noted in any way or mentioned in any
way that this is part of psilocybin
therapy,
because psilocybin is still schedule one,
does it then become all of it will not
get covered?
And if that happens through the course of
the, you know,
chart audit or anything else,
might it be something where individuals
and providers end up having to either
refund the money or potentially get
charged with fraud for that billing.
And so that's why we can't answer that
yet.
And until those questions and we get
definitive yeses, we can't answer that.
And and that's being protective of the
practitioners because we don't want
people being charged with that because
they're trying to do what they think is
the right thing.
And we can't give them that advice until,
you know, until we get to that point.
Sorry, 1st and then we'll go to Greg.
So I'm going to give this little nugget
for people to think about.
I really feel like now we need the, the,
the math nerds.
Sorry for the, the modifier, but you know,
we need some math people being here.
But I'm going to propose this to people
to chew on this.
To Hanifa's point, an end cap of perhaps,
you know,
at 0% cover treatment would be 66150% of
the poverty level.
And that's just throwing it out there,
not saying that this is the thing.
And I was looking at that and it's about
100.
Wait, no, that's wrong.
OK,
so This is why we need math nerds in here.
So someone kind of checked the math on
that one.
I think I probably definitely did it
wrong,
but I was looking at 650% of the poverty
level, and I think that threw me at 137,
000 or something like that as the end cap
to Hanifa's point at where we would zero
out the help of the Department of Health
for that therapy.
And it can be pushed up or down for sure.
And then I lost my other thought.
So I guess we can go ahead and have, yeah.
Hanifa, ask a question.
No, this is great.
I'm glad you're thinking this is working.
Hello for me.
I'm trying to think about what are the
variables that we need to have to build
this scale, right?
Because the first number is 200% was for
an individual.
So are we saying up to six dependence,
8 dependence?
Like feels like that's because you can
pick any arbitrary number unless you know
the dependence and it's kind of just
harder just to pick one number because it
seems like there's going to be a, a whole,
what's the word?
The word isn't coming to me,
but CF cluster things you cannot say no,
the word is matrix.
There's going to be a matrix, right?
It's not just going to be just for one
individual.
So how that's something I'm curious how
we're going to say we're going to go up
to five dependents, 64 dependents,
because it can't be infinite,
but it's got to be something, you know,
we have to set the the parameters.
Yeah.
And I think to the point,
I think this is the other point I was
going to jump off of what Dominic was
saying is, you know,
there are these other variables that are
involved.
And this is, again, math people,
please help me with this.
If we are neglecting gravity for
neglecting all these other things,
what does this look like?
So it's not that we're not going to put
those in because I mean,
I definitely can attest to the fact that
like applying for a scholarship aid with
the college, you know, according to math,
my parents could afford to send me to
school for X amount of money.
That's not the truth.
They could afford like this much.
OK.
So those are the variables that I think
we're going to be having to look at.
I forget what extenuating circumstances,
I can't remember what it's called
extenuating circumstances wherein you're
caring for your elder,
you're caring for your kids.
All of a sudden your car got totaled and
you have all this other stuff that,
you know,
whatever circumstances that life has
brought to your doorstep that you
definitely really need to have the
service.
And,
and so those are the things that we're
going to definitely look at.
But neglecting all those things,
the starting point is this.
And then we can start adding the car,
the kid, the the washer,
blowing out any of these other natural
disasters that we're having to figure out.
Then we can add those in as the variables
for the extenuating circumstances.
And then I'll go ahead and pass it back
to you, Dominic.
Oh, great questions.
Yeah, I think on that, just on that point,
the more we can take away from the
participants the requirement to sift
through all their things and expose that
if we can just like do a standardized
deduction or a cost of living adjustment
to income, we can get this.
We can get people who are requesting a
need into a simple calculation.
So I think the further we get out of the
weeds,
the better it is for the department and
for the people,
the participants who are suffering in
that way.
It becomes for me, if I have,
when I have anxiety and my finances are a
mess,
getting me to go through my own finances
is not something that ever happens.
I'll go through yours,
but that's part of my ADHD response.
I wanted to point on the,
if we are in a position where we're
trying to just kind of like push through
regular therapy sessions as not included,
we need to trace those in the program.
So because of the program's data outcome
efficacy needs,
we need to make sure that the entire
episode of treatment is trapped in like
our data.
So if we have to separate that because
we're financially removing one thing to
outside of the episode of treatment,
then we lose an opportunity to really
provide the depth of efficacy connected
to the entirety of because we're not
doing like this particular way of taking
mushrooms is not going out to the woods
with your friends.
This is a model of like deep life
restructuring.
So anyways,
I just want to make sure that we don't
like get ourselves into a log.
And this is to Hanifa's question as far
as number of dependents.
So these end up being matrixes as you
kind of mentioned.
And what ends up happening is there's
actually a specific dollar amount and I
can't read it on my screen because it's
too small at the moment.
But it like this one particular chart
goes up to 8 dependent and then after
that it's add for each dependent a
certain dollar amount for each.
So we don't actually have to limit that.
And I would hate to do that because if
that were to happen,
my parents would be right at that 8 point
because I'm one of eight kids.
So they would have been at that point.
So yes, great.
That's the things you learned during
committee meetings.
But that's, you know,
so we don't want to necessarily do that
because again,
some of the families that actually are
going to need this the most may actually
have more dependence.
And dependence aren't always children.
They often can be nieces,
nephews who are being cared for.
And so we don't want to eliminate someone
because they have a big heart and they're
really trying to do the best for their
family.
So I would just say we would follow that
same sort of chart and we would just we
would utilize that matrix and say, OK,
beyond that we add it.
And so that's why using the percentage
works because we're not,
we're just giving the numbers as an
example of at a household of one,
this is how much it 200% is,
but it would actually be set up based
upon that entire matrix of based on
dependence and then what the percentage
is.
So I hope that helps.
And and I just want to say we've only got
a a few minutes left at this point,
but I think we've made a good start.
But this by you would kind of set at the
650% sort of being that maximum level.
And so if everybody is OK with that,
what we can do from the program
standpoint is take that minimum and
maximum and sort of figure out a scale in
between just using some mathematics.
We're not going to go into great depth
and detail.
And if that would be OK with everybody
who's here,
we can bring that back to the next group
and say,
what do people think now that you see it
and we can actually have a matrix and
show everyone and then we can adjust up
or down from there.
Does that sound like a good step?
Yeah.
And I can go ahead and give that number
if you want.
Oh, I, no, we'll, we can figure it out.
Oh, yeah.
I just just so that people can hear it.
Oh, it was not just Yeah.
And just for the people listening and,
and this is where I figured out the math.
OK,
so 650% that I'm proposing that we just
kind of put down on paper or pencil in at
this point.
Penciling in the maximum is 650% based on
this chart that we have that we have in
the in the in the chat and that number is
100 and 3740.
Just as to kind of put that in your head
that if you're making that amount,
then it will the treatment cost will then
zero out like you would have to pay the
full cost of the treatment.
So if you're making $103,740,
that's 650% of the poverty level.
And for those who want to do the
calculation, you take 15 point.
Wait, fifteen 1000, sorry, 15,960 * 6.5.
OK,
that's how you do that and you'll come up
with that number.
All right.
And so the proposal is that we're going
to just have that as the zero point.
That's the maximum that the DoH will be
able to provide a cost of treatment for
psilocybin therapy,
medical psilocybin therapy.
So for the next meeting.
So while everyone is toying with those
two numbers where we are providing 100%
at below and then the maximum where we're
zeroing out,
the DoH is going to then do some math and
provide a scale so the rest of us can
look at it and see what that is.
Then we're going to throw in the
variables.
So the other homework for people I would
feel is what are those variables and what
does that look like?
Not that we're actually going to get to
them, but just have them in your pocket.
So elder care, child care, translators,
cost of living,
extenuating circumstances that you can
possibly think of that might be in there.
And then also to Dominic's point,
using this chart,
we are looking at the households within
that 200% poverty level.
OK,
so some of that might be a little bit
much.
And I just did want to point out,
you know,
for for myself and I feel like for all of
us,
our root chakras really going overboard
here because that's the one that deals
with finances and money.
So if we're,
if this is frightening you or in any way
challenging you,
this is if you hear that calling that
this is the challenging part.
This is a part of the work itself,
trying to figure out what,
what the money part of it is.
And for those of you who have already
gotten past that, thank you.
We need your help to help us through this
challenge.
And in that case,
I will hand it back to Dominic.
Do anything else that you needed to?
Any other comments or questions that we
have from the audience?
Any thoughts from someone that's that's
out there in digital land?
So just a couple of comments that we have
here are just some.
I had a question about the who's
discussing the training license
facilitators.
And so that of course is the Training and
Education Committee,
which is meeting on May 8th and is a
combined meeting with the end of life
care committee.
And then whether or not licensed
facilities being organized considered in
more rural areas as access physically is
just as important as financial.
And that was a part of what I had
mentioned earlier about other
possibilities as far as how to get
covered because we recognize that from an
equity standpoint and whether it's about
paying for transportation for the
patients or potentially figuring out ways
to pay or help support providers to go to
those areas.
And then those are all the items in the
chat and just thank you from that
standpoint.
Otherwise what else?
Anyone else in the room have a closing
comment next meeting?
Yeah, we have the,
if anyone has the more written inclined,
Yeah.
And if anybody wants to submit comments,
you can submit them to themedical.
psilocybin@doh.nm.
gov e-mail and we accept those until of
course the next business day at 5:00 PM.
And I'll put the the link to the e-mail
in the chat in just a moment when I'm not
holding a microphone or actually Johnny,
if you don't mind typing it in.
And,
and otherwise we just need to determine
next meeting.
So let's see.
I don't have the calendar.
I'm pulling one up now.
Do you mind if I just a little while
you're looking that up?
So I've been tasked by Dan Jennings along
with a handful of other committee
contributors to work on developing
outcome data collection.
And we've been working on sound like
figuring out how we are managing cultural
considerations for outcome tracking and
and onboarding and like,
you know the whole thing.
So during the May 8th research and
continuous improvement meeting,
it would be very nice to have people
coming to that meeting with the lens of
cultural considerations in how and,
and bringing forth like just thoughts on
how we are like communicating that we're
tracking people and making that not sound
scary.
And then also like finding definitions of
efficacy and how we can, you know,
make make this program do tracking better.
So anyways, that's that's all.
OK.
So what I'm hearing is, you know,
an invitation to those who are equity
access and culturally consider minded who
would like to participate in the next
racy committee meeting on May 8th.
Please definitely come because they're
going to be talking about more cultural
considerations for the research portion
of sometimes for some of us,
a big scary word, data collecting.
And we need diversity.
And yes,
we need diversity because there are some
elements of consideration, you know,
for for that kind of data collection.
It's not always something that we we want
to be able to divulge.
And there's thank God,
there's sometimes an option that says,
you know, decline.
And so we want to know what those things
look like.
And then we've got Don Moser with his
hand up online.
Don,
you should be able to unmute when you're
ready.
Yes,
it may be too late in the conversation,
but do we know how many people are at
certain levels of income in New Mexico?
Like how many people are at the poverty
level,
how many people at the 650% poverty level
and whether or not that would be a factor
in determining the scale?
Thank you, Don.
That's a good question.
And yes, there are charts like that.
I don't have them in front of me right
now, but we could pull those on out.
But I think that it would be,
the issue is it's not going to just be
the general population that that fits in,
that it's going to be the people who need
this particular service and that we don't
have the information on.
So it's a great question, but no,
we don't really have the information on
it.
However,
I think that we can potentially make an
assumption,
although I'm always hesitant to do that
in these kinds of cases because
individuals who often are dealing with
several of these issues often tend to
have other issues with regard to getting
income.
For example,
individuals who have severe PTSD,
it can be very difficult for them from an
employment standpoint.
The same thing with treatment resistant
depression.
And so we probably would be skewing with
whichever way towards the lower end of
the income scale,
not completely because of course,
even though people may have money,
they still often have problems.
But we would be looking at some of those
issues.
And for example, with PTSD,
many of the people and much of the
research that's been done has been with
veterans with PTSD and often who are on
disability.
And so once again,
we're looking at a sort of a skewing of
the scales.
And so I don't think that we have a clear
picture of how many people,
but that's a good point.
And that would be a part of why we would
be looking at this over time to see if
that adjustments after the program's
implemented to see where might this fall
because we really don't necessarily know.
And that's a really great question and
something that we could add in as part of
part of the tracking mechanism of saying
where are individuals falling so we can
make those adjustments with more
knowledge,
because we just don't have that right now.
Like nobody's done a survey at this point,
including us saying who would be eligible
for this,
for this treatment and what income levels
are they at?
I wish somebody had the money to do that.
Kind of to your point,
Greg racy committee,
this is another potential, you know,
crossover where we're looking at that
kind of data.
And for those, you know,
we're we're we're,
we're just starting again,
just we're just starting this.
So I wanted to really close out bit.
So thank you all for your time and your
effort to be present both physically and
also online.
Providing your collective wisdom is
really helpful.
You can can talk to more people and
communicate the importance of what we're
doing and so that we we can continue to
do this work.
I know that for some of us this is,
you know,
uncomfortable or putting ourselves out
there.
And so we just really want to thank you
for doing that,
putting yourselves out there,
moving past that to help all of us
collectively get to a solution and a
starting point so we can move forward
ahead for for everyone's sake is really
important.
So again, thank you all for being here.
Oh, comment next, just next meeting.
Oh, next meeting.
That's great.
So what I was going to propose because
from a department standpoint,
we actually have several things that are
hitting the next couple of Tuesday
afternoons.
Yeah.
So would Tuesday, May 19th, same time,
3:00 work for individuals?
I am going to look at that on the
calendar.
3:00 is clear for me but and I'm seeing
other head nods, anything in chat,
is it problematic for anyone would I
guess be the the better question,
not seeing anything in the chat.
OK,
then we'll see about setting it up for
the 19th.
Nice point.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.
Thank you and thank you again to
everybody both online and here in person.
We really appreciate it.
Thank you.
Have a great day.